we remember that Socrates was known as
the gadfly of Athens because of his
style that was so provocative as he
would go through the marketplace and ask
people penetrating questions and try to
stimulate their thinking so the modern
philosopher who also was given that
descriptive nickname of gadfly was Soren
Kierkegaard who many believe to be the
father of modern existentialism
of course kierkegger guard
lived in Denmark he was born in 1813 and
died in 1855 at the young age of 42.
I remember as a college student being a
philosophy major going through my
Kierkegaard period
because Kierkegaard was passionately
committed to the Christian faith and
after reading so much of the barren
Wasteland of modern philosophy as a
student and we came to the study of
Kierkegaard it was like a breath of
fresh air blowing through the abstract
classrooms of philosophy and so for a
time I more or less fell in love with
cooker guard and read everything I could
get my hands on that he had written and
he was a man of prodigious ability both
in terms of technical philosophy but
also was extremely gifted in a literary
way and it's amazing that somebody who
spoke a language that to the rest of the
world is obscure and emanating from such
a small nation as Denmark that he would
have had the influence on 19th and 20th
Century culture that indeed he did if
there's one word
that summarizes the concern of Soren
Kierkegaard as a philosopher it is the
word
passion
he himself was a passionate man a man of
intense feelings feelings of love and
Devotion to Christ but also his life was
marked by a constant struggle against
the impulses of despair
principally emanating from a lost love
whose name was Regina
which haunted him to the day that he
died now one of the insights that
character guard gave to the world was
his analysis of what he called the
stadia
which is the plural of stadium a stadium
is where one goes to observe some public
event or spectacle like an athletic
contest
and he talked about the three stadia
of life
or sometimes termed the three stages
along life's way where many people
become stuck in one or the other of
these stages in the first Stadium
of the three stadia he called the
aesthetic
Stadium or the aesthetic stage along
life's way
and this is the level of existence
where one becomes and remains chiefly a
spectator
and he includes within this group of
Aesthetics those who are called what he
called epicurean
hedoness
namely those who spend their lives
appreciating admiring and being chiefly
concerned with the pursuit of the
Delight that comes through the Arts
those who like to go to concerts those
who like to go to galleries those who
enjoy being Spectators to other people's
creative genius
and secondly he put in this stage of the
Aesthetics those who were abstract
intellectuals or what we would call
Eggheads
whose heads are in the clouds but remain
divorced from the details of human
existence that get down and dirty in
this regard he once made an observation
about the culture of his day we remember
that Nietzsche had been chiefly critical
of 19th century European culture calling
it decadent because of its lack of of uh
of creativity and its lack of Courage
Kierkegaard said let others complain
that our age is wicked
my complaint is that it is paltry
that it lacks passion he said when I
become depressed with my own culture and
the world around me he said I inevitably
am drawn back to the Old Testament where
I encounter people who are real they lie
they steal they cheat they commit
adultery and yet in the midst of all of
this they have this passionate Pursuit
Of The God Who is
and so he was complaining
of those who passed the time of their
lives on the sidelines who remained
personally and existentially uninvolved
with the great cares and crises of human
existence well the second stage along
life's way according to Kierkegaard he
called
the ethical stage
where people live on the basis of
conscience and are concerned with the
value systems around them
and terms of Good and Evil they are not
simply disinterested spectators
but they are people who are concerned
with value and with
Justice and this of course is an
advanced stage over the aesthetic stage
but it is an intermediate stage to the
ultimate existential stage to which
Kierkegaard was calling people
and Esau
that the that the highest or the deepest
stage along life's way was stage three
which he defined as the religious stage
of human existence
now
uh passion for religion and for the
things of God is what marked this
philosopher's life
and his thinking I mentioned earlier
that as a college student I read
everything I could get my hands on from
Kierkegaard including purity of heart
fear and trembling attack upon
Christendom the concluding unscientific
post-grip either or and
others
in this religious stage
life in its existential passion is
marked according to care guard by the
twin
characteristics of fear and trembling
and he wrote a book by this title in
which the hero of the story is the
biblical patriarch Abraham
and you recall Abraham's existential
anguish when God called him
to the Supreme test whereby he was
commanded of God to take his son the son
whom he loved Isaac and to take him to
Mount Moriah and there to kill him and
offer him as a sacrifice unto God
and in fear and trembling Kierkegaard
tries to pierce the soul of Abraham and
imagine the existential anguish that
Abraham went through as he was
contemplating this enormous Dreadful
task that God had set before him
and one of the key
refrains that that Kierkegaard works
with in fear and trembling is related to
the biblical description of that event
when we're told that after God gives
this command to Abraham The Narrative
says and Abraham rose up early in the
morning
and Kierkegaard begins to contemplate on
that phrase and he asked the question
why did Abraham get up early in the
morning
was it because he was such a virtuous
Sanctified man that he rose up early to
be bright and alert and about the
business of obeying the command of God
well Kierkegaard doesn't think so
character guard thought that the reason
why Abraham got out of his bed in the
morning is because Abraham couldn't
sleep he tossed and turned on his bed he
was in the cot in the throes of
existential anxiety of fear and of
trembling
because God had commanded him to do
something that was absolutely
unthinkable
to destroy his own son who indeed was
the child of promise
and to do this God was commanding
Abraham to do something that the moral
law later is expressed in Moses and
already is expressed in the natural law
written within us
completely for bad The Taking of a human
life in such a manner and child
sacrifice was an Abomination to Israel
and so part of Abraham's anguish was the
anguish of asking himself can this
really be the voice of God this re
involved what Kierkegaard called the
temporary suspension of the ethical
I don't know what that phrase May mean
to you but the only thing I can relate
it to in our day in terms of simple
illustration is the experience you may
have when you're driving through a city
and maybe the traffic lights are not
adequately performing or there's a
traffic jam and instead of going through
the lights as they occur there's a
policeman on the corner
and if you've ever driven your car to an
intersection where a policeman was
directing traffic and the light turned
red
but the policeman motioned you to go
ahead
you have the temporary suspension of the
ethical the law requires that you stop
when the light is red unless
the personal embodiment of the law the
traffic officer is present there to
override it and even then you see people
hesitate to go through a red light even
when the policeman in his uniform is
mostly in you to come through this is
just a a tiny Taste of the thing that
Abraham
struggled with when God told him
to go against the law
and so how does Abraham respond to this
existential crisis
well he does it by taking a leap of
faith
and embracing the Paradox of the moment
and now what what Kierkegaard does at
this point is that he uses this
illustration in the life of Abraham
to
illustrate the whole substance of a
passionate Christian Life
because the Christian faith is a
pilgrimage that requires the existential
leap the time where you have nothing in
front of you but Darkness
and yet you have the command of God to
move ahead and you must leap by trusting
that God will be out there in the
darkness and you must act and you cannot
simply be a spectator or sit around
analyzing what is right and what is
wrong if you know that God is calling
you to something even if you can't see
what's on the other side of the street
just like Abraham you have to take the
existential leap of faith now for
Kierkegaard the existential leap of
faith was not something that was
patently irrational or absurd but it was
something that on the surface seemed to
be irrational and absurd and what
Kierkegaard is saying is that that's the
risk that a person has to take if
they're going to be a follower of Christ
because Christ himself is the Supreme
paradox
because in Christ in his incarnation
we have the intersection of the infinite
with the finite
the Eternal with the temporal
the unconditioned with the conditioned
and that is the Paradox of the one who
is God and man
and so one must
passionately commit oneself to this
Christ of scripture in a moment of
Crisis that became later became called
by theologians the crisis of existential
onshidon or decision
and this moment of passion is the moment
of faith that defines a true authentic
Christian's life
and that takes place he uses the term as
I said moment
the existential moment that is of
decisive significance for one's whole
existence now you remember when we were
studying Descartes and Descartes was
wrestling with the question of the
interaction between act and thought
thought and act mind and matter and he
speculated about the transition that
takes place
in the mind at a given point
and he made reference to his
mathematical understanding of a point
as being something that was
taking up space but had no definite
Dimensions it was kind of a hybrid sort
of hanging between mind and matter an
intermediate point the point of
transition that he used now for
Kierkegaard he speaks not of a point of
Crisis but of a moment of crisis
and what is a moment an algenblik
that moment is something that takes up
time but has no definite duration it is
to time what a point is to linear space
and so Kierkegaard speaks about this
Moment of Truth this moment of decision
where Faith breaks in to the ordinary
linear structure of life and defines
everything from that moment on
the other
person with whom Abraham
so close excuse me that but with whom
Kierkegaard so closely identified from
Biblical literature in addition to
Abraham was the person of job
because job was the man who knew the
profound depths of suffering and of pain
and who was threatened every minute of
his existence with Despair and yet out
of his pain
came
insights
into truth
into love and into Faith you remember
job in the midst of his Affliction
crying out though he slay me
yet will I trust him
and in that sequence job became for
Kierkegaard his spiritual model or ideal
one of the uh
uh
things that that he was concerned about
was how pain and suffering can be
translated into beauty though the one
who is experiencing the anguish and pain
that produces the Beautiful
is not fully appreciated by the public
he's speaking here of the of the woes
and misery suffered by the poet or the
artist and he gave two illustrations
about that the one he told the story of
a man who worked in a theater and his
role was to play the pro part of a clown
and he comes out onto the stage
and as he is going through his act he
sees in the back of the theater an
outbreak of smoke and Fire
and he's alarmed and so he cries out to
the audience that the building is on
fire and when he does that
dressed in his clown outfit
the audience laughs
and the more the clown warns and the
more he cries out about the imminent
danger
the greater the laughter of the people
God says this is what is
the problem with the prophet in any
generation
that he is subjected to ridicule and
mockery another illustration he used was
of a a rebel who had disobeyed the rules
of the king and the punishment that the
king imposed upon him was to be burned
at the stake the problem is the King was
very soft-hearted and he couldn't stand
to watch or to listen to anyone
suffering
and so it was a question as to whether
he would be able to carry out the
execution but they took the rebel and
tied him to the to the post and they
ignited the Flames to burn him at the
stakes and as soon as he cried out in
the throes of Agony the Fates intervened
and translated his screams into
beautiful music
and so the king sat back and said put
more wood on the fire
that I may enjoy more of this beautiful
music
and he says that's the way the public
responds to the poet who creates his
Beauty out of his own pain or the
prophet who brings truth out of his own
suffering
that people enjoy it
without feeling the sickness or the pain
that is being undergone
now in his another small work he talks
on this point which was entitled
sickness unto death
where there he talks about loneliness
and he talks about the condition of what
is called existential Solitude to be
shut up in a world where you are closed
in by yourself he points out that it is
a the Supreme punishment for those who
were incarcerated in prison to be put in
solitary confinement
where one is cut off from all human
intercourse and communication
and he said when a person goes into that
depth of loneliness they are as a person
who has a fatal illness who is sick unto
death who has a desire for one thing and
that is to die
but he can't die he's not allowed to die
and again Kierkegaard is identifying
here personally with job who cried out
to God that God would slay him and take
his life to put him out of his misery
now
for Kierkegaard
one of the great legacies he gave to the
20th century theology was his emphasis
on the subjective aspect of Truth
he was not interested in the cold
abstract logic of Hegel
or of
abstract speculative philosophy or
theology he wrote A A vehement attack
against the institutional church for its
dead Orthodoxy and formalism in his
attack upon Christendom and said that in
his passion to recover the personal
dimension of of authentic truth that
truth is subjectivity
now there's a debate as to what he
whether he really meant what he said was
he simply saying the truth doesn't come
alive until it has the personal
application and appropriation by the
individual or as some of his followers
claimed truth itself is reduced to
personal subjective preference if that
is the case then of course kierkegger
guard has undermined the Christian faith
that he is is espousing by setting the
stage for a later relativism that would
negate the the objective truth of the
word of God but the basic concern of
Kierkegaard at this point
I don't think was to give us a complete
new epistemology or philosophy of truth
but rather to call his generation and
future generations to a passionate
subjective involvement into the life of
faith
that's his legacy to me I believe that
the theology should be rational cogent
coherent logical and all of that
but that our response to that which is
objectively true
should be a response of UN
restrained passion
and care
as we show our love for the things of
God